A Guide to the Rives-Barclay Family Papers, 1698-1941
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Rives-Barclay Family Papers, 1698-1941
Library of Virginia
37776
7.5 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Gerber Publishing Co., Inc., P.O. Box 448, Glenbrook, Nevada 89413 on 22 June 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Col. Thomas Barclay was born on 12 October 1753 in New York City. He was the son of Henry Barclay and Mary Rutgers. He was educated at Columbia College, and married Susan DeLancey on 2 October 1775. He commanded Loyalist forces in New York in 1776, and fled to Nova Scotia at the end of the American Revolution. While residing there he was a practicing lawyer, and was elected a member of the General Assembly, becoming Speaker in 1793. He was also appointed a commissioner to carry out terms of the Jay Treaty in 1795, and served as British Consul-General at New York from 1799 to 1812, and a commssioner under the fourth and fifth articles of the Treaty of Ghent. He died in New York City on 21 April 1830.
His son George Barclay was born at Annapolis, Nova Scotia on 4 July 1790. He married Louisa Anna Matilda Aufrere (1792-1868), the daughter of Anthony Aufrere (1757-1834) and Matilda Lockhart (1774-1850) on 8 December 1818. George Barclay died at New Hamburgh, New York on 28 July 1869.
Their daughter Matilda Antonia Barclay was born in New York City on 7 December 1824. She married Francis Robert Rives (1822- 1891), the son of William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) on 16 May 1848. She died in New York on 25 January 1888.
Their son George Lockhart Rives was born in New York City on 1 May 1849. He attended Columbia College and Trinity College in Cambridge. His father Francis Robert Rives was secretary of legation in London under Edward Everett when the latter was U.S. minister there. George L. Rives received his law degree from Columbia in 1873, and practiced law in New York City. He was Assistant Secretary of State for Latin American Affairs from 1887 to 1889. He married (1) Caroline Morris Kean, and (2) Sara Whiting Belmont. He died in Newport, Rhode Island on 18 August 1917.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1698-1941 (bulk 1790-1880), of the Rives and Barclay families of Albemarle and Nelson Counties, Virginia, and Canada and New York. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1790 to 1880. Includes correspondence, subject files, addresses, articles, booklets, essays, pamphlets, ledgers, letterbooks, prints, and photographs.
Organization
Organized into the following in six series: I. Correspondence. II. Subject Files. III. Addresses, Articles, Booklets, Essays, and Pamphlets. IV. Ledgers and Letterbooks. V. Prints and Photographs. VI. Oversize.
Contents List
- Correspondence (Box 1-7)
  The majority of the collection is the correspondence series. The letters of Thomas Barclay (1753-1830) concern politics, legal matters, family news, business and financial matters, observations on life in America and its citizens after Barclay relocated there from Canada, the escheating of his lands in Nova Scotia after his removal to New York City, and his service as a commissioner appointed to settle the disputed boundary between the United States and Canada. There is also a substantial amount of correspondence concerning the receipt of his pension from the British government. The letters of his son George Barclay (1790- 1869) concern family news and health, financial matters, the estate of his mother-in-law Matilda Lockhart Aufrere (1774-1850), and the sale of family lands in Nova Scotia. There is also correspondence of his brother Henry Barclay (1778-1851) containing family news and information on financial matters. Also included in this series is correspondence of William Cabell Rives (1793-1868) while he was serving as United States Senator from Virginia. The letters are written to his wife Judith Page Walker Rives (1802-1882) and his son Francis Robert Rives (1822-1891). Topics covered include the tariff, appropriations, the Webster Treaty, the presidential election of 1842, Virginia politics, Edward Everett's political career, his own speeches in the Senate, the resignation of Daniel Webster as Secretary of State, reorganization of President Tyler's cabinet, Democratic Party politics, his son's future plans, the annexation of Texas, his opinion of James K. Polk, the appointment of James Buchanan as Secretary of State, and the death of his father Robert Rives (1764-1845).
  The bulk of this series, however, is the correspondence between Francis R. Rives and his wife Matilda Antonia Barclay Rives (1824-1888) and their son George Lockhart Rives (1849-1917) while the latter was a student at Trinity College in Cambridge, England between the years 1868 and 1871. Included are descriptions of his school, his classmates, and the city of London, his social and recreational activities, most notably sailing, his trips to the Continent, his finances and school expenses, the weather, family news, and his parents' trips to Europe. There are also letters written to him by Hamilton Fish (1849-1936) while the latter was serving as private secretary to his father who was United States Secretary of State.
  - Thomas Barclay, 1792-1826 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Barclay, 1828-1829 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - George Barclay, 1843-1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Henry Barclay, 1839-1841, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - William Cabell Rives, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William Cabell Rives, 1843 (January-March) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Cabell Rives, 1843 (April-December) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - William Cabell Rives, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - William Cabell Rives, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - William Cabell Rives, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Edward Everett, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1858-1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1864 (January-July) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1864 (August) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1864 (September-December) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1865-1867 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1868 (January-February) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1868 (June-July) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1868 (August) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1868 (September) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1868 (October) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1868 (November) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1868 (December) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1869 (January) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1869 (February) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1869 (March) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1869 (April) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1869 (May) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1869 (June) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1869 (July) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1869 (August) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1869 (September) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1869 (October) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1869 (November) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1870 (January) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1870 (February) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1870 (March) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1870 (April) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1870 (May) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1870 (June) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1870 (July) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1870 (August 1-15) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1870 (August 16-31) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1870 (September) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1870 (October) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1870 (November) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1870 (December) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1871 (January) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1871 (February) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1871 (March) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1871 (April) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1871 (May) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1871 (June) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1871 (July) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1871 (August) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1871 (September) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1871 (October) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1871 (November) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1871 (December) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1872 (January) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1872 (February-March) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1872 (April-May) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 1872 (June-August) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 1872 (September-December) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1873 (January-June) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1873 (July) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1873 (August-December) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1874 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1875 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1877 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1878 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1880 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1881 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1883 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1884 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 1885 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - 1886 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - 1887 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - 1892 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - 1941 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - n.d. (Aufrere, Caroline) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - n.d. (Aufrere, George) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - n.d. (Livingston, Robert C.) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - n.d. (Lockhart, P. N.) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - n.d. (Rives, Constance) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - n.d. (Rives, Ella) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - n.d. (Rives, Matilda A.) (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
  - n.d. (Rives, George L.) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - n.d. (Various Individuals) (Box 7, Folder 11-13)
- Subject Files (Box 8)
  The subject files contain a variety of material on the Aufrere, Barclay, DeLancey, Lockhart, and Rives families. Included are calling cards and invitations, information on the dower claim of Margaret DeLancey who was the widow of James DeLancey, estate papers, genealogical notes, military service records, the pension claim of Susan Barclay who was the widow of Thomas Barclay, speeches, and the wills of Matilda Lockhart Aufrere and Thomas Barclay.
  - Appointment of Supervisors of Bell Isle Marsh - Petition and Bill (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Benson v. DeLancey, 1798 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Calling Cards and Invitations (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Clippings (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Columbia College Cards and Programs, 1868 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Columbia College - Philolexian Society, 1868 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Dower Claim of Margaret DeLancey, 1802-1803 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Estate Papers of George A. Aufrere, 1881-1889 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Estate Papers of Henry Barclay (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Estate Papers of Thomas Barclay (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Estate Papers of Oliver DeLancey (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Estate Papers of Stephen DeLancey (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Estate Papers of Schulyer Livingston (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Genealogical Notes - Aufrere Family (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Genealogical Notes (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 16-17)
    - Barclay Family (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Lockhart Family (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Rives Family (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Whiting Family (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - George Washington Portrait (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Guardians of the Orphans of George R. Belasise (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Law Licenses of Francis R. Rives, 1847 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Legislative Acts (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Letter - William Cabell Rives to Col. Edmund Fontaine, 1 January 1844 (transcription) (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Military Service of DeLancey Barclay, 1800-1826 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Military Service of Thomas Barclay, 1799-1838 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Patent Design (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Pension Claim of Susan Barclay (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Speech - Rives, George L. "Whom Should We Vote For for President and Vice-President of the United States?" - Wappingers Falls, Dutchess County, New York, 4 October 1884 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - William Cabell Rives (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 30-32)
    - Letter of Resignation as Minister to France, 1853 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Speech - State Agricultural Society of New York, Saratoga (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Drafts of Speeches and Letters (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Will of Matilda Lockhart Aufrere (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Will of Thomas Barclay (Box 8, Folder 34)
- Addresses, Articles, Booklets, Essays, and Pamphlets (Box 9-10)
  Most of these items relate to the work of George L. Rives. Included is the manuscript copy of his valedictory address at Columbia College (1869), articles on the United States and Mexico relations, which he wrote a book on, essays he wrote while at Cambridge, and various pamphlets containing speeches by members of the U.S. House of Representative and Senate, including his grandfather, William Cabell Rives. Many of these concern the annexation of Texas.
  - Addresses (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Rives, George L. "A Memorial of George Bancroft" (1892) (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Rives, George L. "Some Unsettled Legal Problems Affecting the Government of Cities" (1904) (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Rives, George L. - Valedictory Oration (1868) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Articles (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4-16)
    - Barker, Eugene C. "The United States and Mexico, 1835-1837" Mississippi Valley Historical Review, vol. 1 (June, 1914) (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Garland, Hamlin. "Grant in the Mexican War" McClures (February, 1897) (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Grayson, Andrew J. "An Ornithologist in Mexico" Overland Monthly (September, 1871) (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Janvier, Thomas A. "The Mexican Army" Harper's New Monthly Magazine (November, 1889) (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Reeves, J. S. "The Treaty of Guadalupe-Hidalgo" (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Reilly, James. "An Artilleryman's Story" The Journal Military Service Institution, vol. 33, no. 126 (Nov.-Dec. 1903) (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Rives, George L. "Court of Appeals Calendar" Albany Law Journal, vol. 31, no. 8 (21 February 1885) (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Rives, George L. "Mexican Diplomacy on the Eve of the War with the United States" American Historical Review, vol. XVIII, no. 2 (January, 1913) (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Rives, George L. "The Site of Columbia University" Fortnightly Bulletin, vol. 1, no. 11 (13 March 1914) (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Rives, George L. "Problems of an Inter-Oceanic Canal" Political Science Quarterly, vol. XIV, no. 2, (June, 1899) (Box 9)
    - Rives, George L. "Spain and the United States in 1795" American Historical Review, vol. IV, no. 1 (October, 1898) (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Victor, Mrs. F. F. "A Short Stay in Acapulco" Overland Monthly (March, 1871) (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - "General Crook in the Indian Country" The Century Magazine, vol. XLI, no. 5 (March, 1891) (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - "Life in the Mexican Capital" Old Guard (July, 1870) (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Booklets (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 17-20)
    - Borland, Constance. The Borland Family (1911) (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Apuntes Biograficos del Senor General Luis Mier y Teran Gobernador Constitucional del Estado Libre y Soberano de Veracruz Llave (1879) (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Rives, George L. An Essay on the Authorship of the First, Second, and Third Parts of Henry the Sixth, Commonly Attributed to Shakespeare (1874) (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Manifestacion que hace al Publico el Juez 20 del Ramo Criminal de Mexico, Lic. Don Teofilo Carrasquedo, en Defensa.... (1856) (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Essays (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 21 -27)
    - Rives, George L. "Can Natural Theology Ever Become a Progressive Science?" (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Rives, George L. "English Literature in the Reigns of William III and Anne" (4 October 1871) (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Rives, George L. "The Knights Templars" (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Rives, George L. "Physiognomy" (18 March 1871) (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Rives, George L. "The Progress of American Literature" (24 May 1866) (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Rives, George L. "Saint Telemachus" (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Rives, George L. "Subrogation as Applied to Suretyship" (April, 1873) (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Pamphlets (Box 10)
    - Auction Catalogue, 1847 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Auction Catalogue, 1848 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Barber, A. W. The Benevolent Raid of General Lew Wallace - How Mexico Was Saved in 1864 - The Monroe Doctorine In Action (1914) (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Battles of Mexico: Containing an Authentic Account of All Battles Fought in the Republic from the Commencement of the War until the Capture of the City of Mexico: With a List of the Killed and Wounded (1847) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Baylies, Francis. A Narrative of Major General Wool's Campaign in Mexico in the Years 1846, 1847 & 1848 (1851) (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Bayly, Thomas H. Speech in the U.S. House of Representatives on the Annexation of Texas to the United States (1845) (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Belser, James E. Speech in the U.S. House of Representatives on the Annexation of Texas to the United States (1845) (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Calhoun, John C. Speech in the U.S. Senate on His Resolutions in Reference to the War with Mexico (1848) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Ceremonial para la Consagracion de la Cathedral de Mexico y su Nuevo Tabernaculo (1850) (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Gallatin, Albert. Peace With Mexico (1847) (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Giddings, J. R. Speech in the U.S. House of Representatives on the Annexation of Texas (1845) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Holmes, Isaac E. Speech in the U.S. Senate on the Annexation of Texas to the United States (1845) (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - In the Matter of the Petition of Beverley Robinson, Trustee, and George Barclay and Schulyer Livingston, Creditors of William James St. John, Deceased (1847) (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Letter from the Hon. Hugh S. Legare, on the Probable Effects of the Sub-Treasury Policy with the Specie Clause, to His Excellency Pierce Butler, Governor of South Carolina (1838) (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Letters from the Hon. Abbott Lawrence to the Hon. William C. Rives of Virginia (1846) (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Logan, Walter S. The Siege of Cuautla: The Bunker Hill of Mexico (1893) (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Memoria del Secretario de Estado y del Despacho de la Guerra, presentada a las Cameras en Enero de 1825 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Parsons, George M. Biographical Sketch of the Late Gustavus Swan (1885) (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Parte de las Operaciones Ejecutadas por la Tercera Brigada de Ynfanteria del Ejercito Mexicano (1847) (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Relacion de los Sucesos Acaecidos en la Ciudad de Puebla, del 14 al 27 de Mayo de 1847 (1901) (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Rives, George L. Railway Companies and the Civil Code (1887) (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Rives, George L. Torts Under the Code (1885) (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. House of Representatives on the Mission to Panama (1826) (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. Senate on the Bill Further to Provide of the Collection of Duties on Imports (1833) (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Remarks on Resigning His Seat in the Senate of the United States (1834) (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. Senate on the Subject of the Removal of Deposits (1834) (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. Senate on the Currency of the United States, and the Collection of the Public Revenue (1837) (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. Senate in Support of the Bill Introduced by Him Designating the Funds Receivable in Payment of the Public Revenue and in Opposition to the Sub-Treasury Scheme (1837) (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. Senate on the Treaty with Great Britain (1842) (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Rives, William Cabell. Speech in the U.S. Senate on the Annexation of Texas (1845) (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Rockwell, Julius. Speech in the U.S. House of Representatives Upon the Question of the Admission of Texas as a State into the Union (1845) (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Shackford, Charles C. A Citizen's Appeal in Regard to the War with Mexico (1848) (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Thoughts on the Proposed Annexation of Texas to the United States (1844) (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - The Virginia Historical Register and Literary Advertiser (January, 1848) (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Ledgers and Letterbooks (Box 11-15)
  The ledgers and letterbooks were kept by Anthony and Matilda Aufrere, Thomas Barclay, George Barclay, and George L. Rives. Those belonging to Anthony and Matilda Aufrere contain various pieces of verse and prose. The letterbooks of Thomas Barclay contain his official correspondence while he was stationed in New York serving as British Consul-General for the Eastern States off America. There are 13 volumes. The last volume also contains letters written while he was serving as a commissioner under the fourth and fifth articles of the Treaty of Ghent to settle the ongoing dispute over the Canadian-U.S. boundary. Portions of these letterbooks were published in Selections from the Correspondence of Thomas Barclay - Formerly British Consul-General at New York by George Lockhart Rives (New York: Harper & Bros., 1894). Also included in this series are three letterbooks of George Barclay covering the years 1850-1856 and 1861-1868 while he was a merchant in New York. There is also a ledger of George L. Rives containing official correspondence, proceedings, and regulations while he was serving as Assistant Secretary of State for Latin American Affairs from 1887 to 1889.
  - Collectanea (Ledger of Verse and Prose Belonging to Anthony and Matilda Aufrere) (Box 11)
  - Fugitive Pieces in Verse and Prose, Vols. 1 & 2, 1799 (Belonging to Anthony and Matilda Aufrere) (Box 11)
  - Private Notes on Boats, 1870 (Belonging to George L. Rives) (Box 11)
  - Thomas Barclay Family Expense Books, 1816-1830 (3 vol.) (Box 11)
  - Thomas Barclay Misc. Account Book, 1817-1821 (Box 11)
  - Household Expenses Book, n.d. (Box 11)
  - The Arms of Norris and Playters, 23 April 1770 (Box 11)
  - Norris-Aufrere-Lockhart Genealogical Notes (Box 11)
  - Letterbooks of Thomas Barclay (Box 12-13)
    - 1 October 1790 - 23 August 1793 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 30 May 1796 - 8 March 1800 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 18 October 1796 - 22 January 1801 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 10 March 1800 - 30 June 1803 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 4 January 1801 - 5 July 1803 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 6 July 1803 - 21 March 1804 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 24 March 1804 - 28 December 1804 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 12 July 1804 - 21 February 1805 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 22 February 1805 - 27 March 1806 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 4 April 1806 - 22 March 1807 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 23 March 1807 - 23 September 1811 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 27 November 1811 - 12 June 1812, and 2 September 1815 - 4 February 1818 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Letterbooks of George Barclay (Box 14)
    - 19 December 1850 - 17 December 1853 (Box 14)
    - 27 December 1853 - 11 December 1856 (Box 14)
    - 3 May 1861 - 20 October 1868 (Box 14)
  - Letterbook of George L. Rives, Assistant Secretary of State, 1887-1889 (Box 15)
- Prints and Photographs (Box 16-19)
  The prints contained in the collection deal with the Mexican War. There are also family photographs and photographs taken on a trip to Mexico, as well as a family photgraph album, and a photograph album of various New York officials, circa 1904.
  - Prints (Box 16)
    - Battle of Buena Vista (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Battle of Chapultepec (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Battle of Cerro Gordo (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Battle of Churubusco (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Battle of Contreras (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Battle of Molino del Ray (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Battle of Monterey (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Battle of Palo Alto (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Battle of Resaca de la Palma (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Buchanan, James (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Capitulation of Vera Cruz (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Death of Major Ringgold at the Battle of Palo Alto (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Houston, Sam (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Polk, James K. (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Scenes in the War with Mexico (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Scott, Winfield (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Gen. Scott's Entry into the City of Mexico (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Taylor, Zachary (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - War in Mexico (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Family Photographs (Box 17, Folder 1-7)
  - Photographs of Mexico (Box 17)
  - Family Photograph Album (Box 18)
  - Photograph Album of New York Officials, ca. 1904 (Box 19)
- Oversize (Box 20 and Map Case G-14/Drawer 10)